<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema/master/tei-pta.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dok. 9: Fragment eines Briefes des Eusebius von Caesarea an Alexander von Alexandrien (Urk. 7)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="AvS">Annette von Stockhausen</persName>
               <resp>Conversion to CTS-compliant PTA TEI.</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Arbeitsstelle Athanasius Werke, FAU Erlangen-Nürnberg</authority>
            <distributor>Patristic Text Archive</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/de/">Available under a Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Germany (CC BY-NC 3.0 DE)</licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2018</date>
            <idno type="PTA">pta0100.pta009</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl>
                  <note>Critical edition (without critical apparatus)</note>
                  <title>Athanasius Werke. Band 3 / 1. Teil: Dokumente zur Geschichte des arianischen Streites. Lieferung 3: Bis zur Ekthesis makrostichos</title>
                  <editor>
                     <forename>Hanns Christof</forename>
                     <surname>Brennecke</surname>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <forename>Uta</forename>
                     <surname>Heil</surname>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <forename>Annette</forename>
                     <surname>von Stockhausen</surname>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <forename>Angelika</forename>
                     <surname>Wintjes</surname>
                  </editor>
                  <pubPlace>Berlin/New York</pubPlace>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="85" to="86">85–86</biblScope>
                  <date when="2007">2007</date>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(.+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']/tei:div[@n='$1'])"/>
         </refsDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>
            This file is encoded according to the guidelines of the Patristic Text Archive (PTA). See <ref target="https://pta.bbaw.de/project/encoding-guidelines">https://pta.bbaw.de/project/encoding-guidelines</ref> and <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3737666">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3737666</ref>.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="biblical-quotations"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Biblical quotations are not annotated and not referenced. References follow the scheme declared <ref target="#biblical">above</ref>.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="other-references"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Other references are not annotated and not referenced. References to texts in the PTA follow the scheme declared <ref target="#pta">above (pta)</ref>, references to texts available in the <ref target="https://scaife.perseus.org/">Perseus Digital Library</ref> follow the scheme declared <ref target="#perseus">above (perseus)</ref>. If the referenced text is not available in either repository, the reference for the referenced text is given in the attribute @source in the form “Authorabbrev_Workabbrev_Location”; ancient Greek authors should be referenced according to the lists of H. G. Liddell/R. Scott/H. S. Jones, A Greek - English Lexicon, Oxford 1968 (9th edition) and G. W. H. Lampe, A Patristic Greek Lexicon, Oxford 1987 (3rd edition), for Latin ones the abbreviations of the Thesaurus Linguae Latinae (cf. Index librorum scriptorum inscriptionum ex quibus exempla afferuntur) should be used, with dots in the abbreviations deleted without replacement.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="persons"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Persons are not annotated and not  referenced with IDs according to the <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/tipnr_data">TIPNR - Tyndale Individualised Proper Names with all References</ref> list for biblical persons and IDs of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/pta_metadata/blob/main/pta_persons.json">PTA persons index</ref> for all other persons.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="groups"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Groups of persons and organisations are not annotated and not referenced with IDs according to the IDs of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/pta_metadata/blob/main/pta_groups.json">PTA groups index</ref> for all other groups.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="places"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Places are not annotated and not referenced with <ref target="https://pleiades.stoa.org/">Pleiades Gazetteer</ref> IDs.
          </p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p><!--Usage of capitalisation, ν-ephelkystikon, σ: οὕτως, Iota subscriptum/adscriptum, Trema, Enclitics, apostroph/elisions, number signs, splitting of words, nomina sacra, ...--></p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p><!--Usage (and/or normalisation) of full stop, comma, semicolon, question mark, dash and parenthesis--></p>
            </punctuation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="comphistsem">
               <bibl>
          Text Type Classification by <ref target="https://www.comphistsem.org/46.html">"Computational Historical Semantics</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="editionstatus">
               <bibl>
          Patristic Text Archive Status of edition
        </bibl>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition">
                  <catDesc>
            Critical edition in which the text-critical variants have been encoded.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition-no-app">
                  <catDesc>
            Critical edition in which the text-critical variants have not been encoded, e.g. because it is a retro-digitisation of a printed critical edition and for copyright reasons the apparatus cannot be included in the retro-digitisation.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition-outdated">
                  <catDesc>
              Edition which notes text-critical variants, but does not, for example, comprehensively include the manuscripts.
            </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="pre-critical-edition">
                  <catDesc>
              Pre-modern editions (e.g. editions in the Patrologia Graeca or Latina)
            </catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="annotationstatus">
               <bibl>
          Patristic Text Archive Status of annotation
        </bibl>
               <category xml:id="fully-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            All instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="partially-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            Some instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="not-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            No instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="fully-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            All encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="partially-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            Some encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="not-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            No encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <schemaRef key="v3"
                    url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema/master/tei-pta.rng"/>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notBefore="0030" notAfter="0800"/>
            <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/XXXXX">
                    placeName missing
                </placeName>
         </creation>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#comphistsem">
               <term>
                        Genre missing
                    </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2023-05-22" who="#AvS">
          Updated file to comply with version 3.0 of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema">TEI-PTA-Schema</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2019-02-10" who="#AvS">Converted to PTA/CapiTainS</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="translation"
              xml:lang="deu"
              n="urn:cts:pta:pta0100.pta009.pta-deu1"
              corresp="urn:cts:pta:pta0100.pta009.pta-grc1">
            <head>
               <title>Dok. 9: Fragment eines Briefes des Eusebius von Caesarea an Alexander von Alexandrien (Urk. 7)</title>
            </head>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
               <p>Desgleichen aber auch im Brief an den heiligen Alexander, den Lehrer des großen Athanasius, dessen Anfang lautet:</p>
               <p>Unter so großer Aufregung und Besorgnis darüber traf der Brief ein.</p>
               <p>Aufs eindeutigste lästernd sagt er über Arius und seine Anhänger folgendes:</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
               <p>Dein Brief klagt sie an, daß sie sagen, der Sohn sei aus nichts geworden wie eines von allen Geschöpfen. Sie aber brachten ihr eigenes
                          Schriftstück vor, das sie an dich gerichtet und in dem sie ihren eigenen Glauben dargelegt haben und mit folgenden Worten so bekannten: »Der Gott des Gesetzes und der Propheten und des neuen Bundes zeugte den einziggeborenen Sohn vor ewigen Zeiten, durch den er auch die Zeiten und das All gemacht hat, gezeugt nicht dem Anschein nach, sondern in Wahrheit, ins Dasein gerufen durch seinen eigenen Willen, unveränderlich und unwandelbar, ein vollkommenes Geschöpf Gottes, doch nicht wie eins der Geschöpfe.« Wenn also nun ihr Schriftstück die Wahrheit sagt, in dem sie den Sohn Gottes vor ewigen Zeiten bekennen, durch den er auch die Zeiten gemacht hat, dann muß dir auch vorgelegen haben, daß er unwandelbar und vollkommenes Geschöpf Gottes ist, aber nicht wie eines der Geschöpfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
               <p>Dein Brief beschuldigt sie aber, daß sie sagen, der Sohn sei geworden wie eines der Geschöpfe. Da sie das aber nicht sagen, sondern deutlich definieren, daß er nicht »wie eines der Geschöpfe ist«, sieh zu, daß ihnen damit nicht wiederum sogleich ein Anlaß gegeben wird, sich daran zu machen, etwas zu unternehmen und Unruhe zu stiften, sooft sie nur wollen.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
               <p>Ferner hast du sie beschuldigt, sie würden sagen, daß »der, der ist, den, der nicht ist, gezeugt hat«. Ich wundere mich aber, ob jemand das anders formulieren kann. Denn wenn der, der ist, einer ist, ist es doch offensichtlich, daß alles aus ihm wurde, was auch nach ihm ist. Falls aber nicht er allein der ist, der ist, sondern auch der Sohn der war, der ist, wie zeugte dann der, der ist, den, der ist? Denn dann dürften es wohl zwei sein, die sind.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
               <p>So also Eusebius an den berühmten Alexander; aber auch weitere Briefe von ihm an denselben heiligen Mann werden vorgelegt, in denen vielerlei Lästerungen zu finden sind, die Arius und seine Anhänger rechtfertigen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
