<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema/master/tei-pta.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>De die dominica (Versio A)</title>
            <author>
               <persName key="pta0030">Eusebius (»Alexandrinus«)</persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName xml:id="AvS">Annette von Stockhausen</persName>
               <roleName>Translator</roleName>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <p>New digital English translation from the Greek text.</p>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Patristic Text Archive</publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Available under a
                  Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2022</date>
            <idno type="PTA">pta0030.pta016</idno>
            <idno type="CPG">5525</idno>
            <idno type="BHG">635c</idno>
            <idno type="Pinakes-Oeuvre">12440</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(.+)"
               replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']/tei:div[@n='$1'])"
            />
         </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl xml:id="biblical">
            <cRefPattern matchPattern="(.+):(.+):([0-9]+):([0-9]+)[\-\.]*[0-9]*"
               replacementPattern="https://www.bibelwissenschaft.de/bibelstelle/$2$3,$4/$1">
               <p>Noted are references to a biblical book, chapter, verse, sc. LXX:Gn:1:1; also
                  possible: LXX:Gn:1:1-3 for a sequence of verses or LXX:Gn:1:1.3 for two verses not
                  following each other.</p>
               <p>The following abbreviations are used: Gn, Ex, Lv, Num, Dt, Jos, Judg, Rt, 1Sa,
                  2Sa, 1Ko, 2Ko, 1Chr, 2Chr, 3Esr, Esr, Est, Jdt, Tob, 1Mak, 2Mak, 3Mak, 4Mak, Ps,
                  Oden, Prov, Eccl, Song, Job, Wis, Sir, PsSal, Hos, Am, Mi, Joel, Ob, Jon, Nah,
                  Hab, Zeph, Hag, Sach, Mal, Is, Jr, Bar, Lam, EpistJer, Hes, Sus, Dn, Bel; Mt, Mk,
                  Lk, Jn, Act, Rom, 1Cor, 2Cor, Gal, Eph, Phil, Col, 1Th, 2Th, 1Tim, 2Tim, Tt, Phm,
                  Heb, Jak, 1P, 2P, 1Jn, 2Jn, 3Jn, Jud, Rev.</p>
            </cRefPattern>
            <cRefPattern matchPattern="(.+):(.+):([0-9]+)[\-\.]*[0-9]*"
               replacementPattern="https://www.bibelwissenschaft.de/bibelstelle/$2$3/$1">
               <p>Noted are references to a biblical book and chapter, sc. LXX:Gn:1; also possible:
                  LXX:Gn:1-3 for a sequence of chapters or LXX:Gn:1.3 for two chapters not following
                  each other.</p>
            </cRefPattern>
            <cRefPattern matchPattern="(.+):(.+)"
               replacementPattern="https://www.bibelwissenschaft.de/bibelstelle/$2/$1">
               <p>Noted are references to a biblical book, sc. LXX:Gn.</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl xml:id="pta">
            <cRefPattern matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://pta.bbaw.de/text/$1">
               <p>References to PTA-CTS-URNs</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl xml:id="perseus">
            <cRefPattern matchPattern="(.+)"
               replacementPattern="https://scaife.perseus.org/reader/$1">
               <p>References to Perseus-CTS-URNs</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p> This file is encoded according to the guidelines of the Patristic Text Archive
                  (PTA). See <ref target="https://pta.bbaw.de/project/encoding-guidelines"
                     >https://pta.bbaw.de/project/encoding-guidelines</ref> and <ref
                     target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3737666"
                     >https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3737666</ref>. </p>
               <p xml:id="biblical-quotations" ana="fully-annotated fully-identified"> Biblical
                  quotations are fully annotated and fully referenced. References follow the scheme
                  declared <ref target="#biblical">above</ref>. </p>
               <p xml:id="other-references" ana="fully-annotated fully-identified"> Other references
                  are fully annotated and fully referenced. References to texts in the PTA follow
                  the scheme declared <ref target="#pta">above (pta)</ref>, references to texts
                  available in the <ref target="https://scaife.perseus.org/">Perseus Digital
                     Library</ref> follow the scheme declared <ref target="#perseus">above
                     (perseus)</ref>. If the referenced text is not available in either repository,
                  the reference for the referenced text is given in the attribute @source in the
                  form “Authorabbrev_Workabbrev_Location”; ancient Greek authors should be
                  referenced according to the lists of H. G. Liddell/R. Scott/H. S. Jones, A Greek -
                  English Lexicon, Oxford 1968 (9th edition) and G. W. H. Lampe, A Patristic Greek
                  Lexicon, Oxford 1987 (3rd edition), for Latin ones the abbreviations of the
                  Thesaurus Linguae Latinae (cf. Index librorum scriptorum inscriptionum ex quibus
                  exempla afferuntur) should be used, with dots in the abbreviations deleted without
                  replacement. </p>
               <p xml:id="persons" ana="fully-annotated fully-identified"> Persons are fully
                  annotated and fully referenced with IDs according to the <ref
                     target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/tipnr_data">TIPNR - Tyndale
                     Individualised Proper Names with all References</ref> list for biblical persons
                  and IDs of <ref
                     target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/pta_metadata/blob/main/pta_persons.json"
                     >PTA persons index</ref> for all other persons. </p>
               <p xml:id="groups" ana="fully-annotated fully-identified"> Groups of persons and
                  organisations are fully annotated and fully referenced with IDs according to the
                  IDs of <ref
                     target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/pta_metadata/blob/main/pta_groups.json"
                     >PTA groups index</ref> for all other groups. </p>
               <p xml:id="places" ana="fully-annotated fully-identified"> Places are fully annotated
                  and fully referenced with <ref target="https://pleiades.stoa.org/">Pleiades
                     Gazetteer</ref> IDs. </p>
            </interpretation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="comphistsem">
               <bibl> Text Type Classification by <ref target="https://www.comphistsem.org/46.html"
                     >"Computational Historical Semantics</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="editionstatus">
               <bibl> Patristic Text Archive Status of edition </bibl>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition">
                  <catDesc> Critical edition in which the text-critical variants have been encoded.
                  </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition-no-app">
                  <catDesc> Critical edition in which the text-critical variants have not been
                     encoded, e.g. because it is a retro-digitisation of a printed critical edition
                     and for copyright reasons the apparatus cannot be included in the
                     retro-digitisation. </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition-outdated">
                  <catDesc> Edition which notes text-critical variants, but does not, for example,
                     comprehensively include the manuscripts. </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="pre-critical-edition">
                  <catDesc> Pre-modern editions (e.g. editions in the Patrologia Graeca or Latina)
                  </catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="annotationstatus">
               <bibl> Patristic Text Archive Status of annotation </bibl>
               <category xml:id="fully-annotated">
                  <catDesc> All instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons,
                     places) are encoded with the respective element. </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="partially-annotated">
                  <catDesc> Some instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons,
                     places) are encoded with the respective element. </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="not-annotated">
                  <catDesc> No instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places)
                     are encoded with the respective element. </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="fully-identified">
                  <catDesc> All encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations,
                     persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data. </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="partially-identified">
                  <catDesc> Some encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations,
                     persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="not-identified">
                  <catDesc> No encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons,
                     places) are identified with the respective norm data. </catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <schemaRef key="v3"
            url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema/master/tei-pta.rng"/>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notBefore="0030" notAfter="1500"/>
            <placeName/>
         </creation>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#comphistsem">
               <term>Paraenetic</term>
               <term>Sermon</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2023-05-22" who="#AvS"> Updated file to comply with version 3.0 of <ref
               target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema">TEI-PTA-Schema</ref>
         </change>
         <change who="#AvS" when="2022-10-30">Translation</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:pta:pta0030.pta016.pta-eng1"
            corresp="urn:cts:pta:pta0030.pta016.pta-grc2">
            <head>
               <title>Speech by the blessed bishop Eusebius (of Alexandria) on the day of the
                  Lord.</title>
            </head>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
               <p>After the release from church on the holy day of the Lord, while the blessed
                  bishop Eusebius sat down, Alexander came forward and asked him: “I beg you, my
                  Lord, why is it necessary to keep the day of the Lord and not to work? And what
                  kind of gain do we have, if we do not work?” The blessed opened his mouth and
                  said: “Hear, child, and I will tell you, why it is taught to us to keep the day of
                  the Lord and not to work. <quote>When the Lord taught his disciples the mystery
                     (of Eucharist), he took the bread, blessed it and breaking it gave it to his
                     disciples and said: ‘Take, eat, this is my body, which is broken for you, for
                     remission of sins.’ Likewise he also gave them the cup and said: ‘You all,
                     drink from it, this is my blood of the new covenant, which is poured out for
                     you, the many, for remission of sins. Do that for my remembrance,’ he says.<ref
                        decls="#biblical" cRef="NA:1Cor:11:23-26"/><ref decls="#biblical"
                        cRef="NA:Mt:26:26-29"/></quote> Therefore, the holy day of the Lord is
                  remembrance. That’s why it is called day of the Lord, as it is lord over the days.
                  For before the passion of the Lord, it was not called Lord’s day, but first day.
                  On that day the Lord began the first-fruits of the creation. And on exactly that
                  day he gave the world the first-fruit of the resurrection, on that day, as we
                  said, he also ordered the holy mysteries to be performed. Now, we have the
                  beginning of all goodness on such a day, the beginning of the creation of the
                  world, the beginning of the resurrection, the beginning of the week. Three
                  beginnings has that day, it dawns the beginning of the most-holy trinity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
               <p>Well, seven days has the week, God gave us six days to work, and he gave us one
                  for prayer, rest, and deliverance from evil and that we may make atonement for
                  them before God on the day of the Lord, if we did sinful actions during the six
                  days. Get up before dawn in the church of God, come to the Lord, confess him your
                  sins, repent in prayer and with a contrite heart, stay in the divine and holy
                  liturgy, complete your prayer and never leave before the release! Look, how your
                  Lord is cut in pieces and distributed and is not eaten up! And if you have a good
                  conscience, come forward and take part in the body and the blood of the Lord! But
                  if your conscience condemns you for bad and foul deeds, decline the community
                  until you amend yourself in repentance, but stay for the prayer and do not leave
                  the church, if you are not released. Remind yourself of <persName type="biblical"
                     key="Judas_Mat.10.4">Judas</persName> the traitor! <seg type="allusion">The
                     beginning of his destruction was that he did not stay with the others praying.
                     When he (Jesus), it says, took the bread, he (Judas) as first of all left and
                     at once Satan entered him, and he eagerly betrayed the Lord.<ref
                        decls="#biblical" cRef="NA:Jn:13:26-30"/></seg> Now, if you leave before the
                  release, you impersonate <persName type="biblical" key="Judas_Mat.10.4"
                     >Judas</persName>. Certainly, you do not want to get judged with <persName
                     type="biblical" key="Judas_Mat.10.4">Judas</persName> because of a little time!
                  Staying doesn’t hurt you. The church has no snow inside, no fire, no other thing
                  tormenting you, but only a small amount of patience is needed and your prayer is
                  perfect.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
               <p>We keep the day of the Lord only to stay away from work and to have opportunity to
                  pray. But if you stay away from work and do not go to church, you gain nothing. To
                  the contrary, you hurt yourself greatly. Many wait for the day of the Lord, but
                  not all for the same end. Those who have fear for God wait for the day of the
                  Lord, that they may send their prayer to God and enjoy the dear body and blood.
                  But the careless and the negligent wait for the day of the Lord that they may stay
                  away from work and spend their time with bad people. And what happened gives
                  evidence that I do not lie: Go to the main street on any day and you will find
                  nobody. Go on the day of the Lord and you will find some playing the lyre, others
                  beating and dancing, others sitting and joking with their neighbor and scolding,
                  others wrestling, others wrangling with each other, others nodding to bad things,
                  and if somewhere there is a lyre and a dance, then all run. The announcer calls to
                  the church and all display hesitation and inability. A sound of the lyre or of the
                  flute or a beat of dancing is produced, and all come there very fast as if they
                  had wings. What do those who come to church look at? I say it to you: the Lord
                  Christ offered on the holy table while the Seraphim sing the three-holy hymn, the
                  Holy Spirit’s arrival and visit, the prophet and king <persName type="biblical"
                     key="David_Rut.4.17">David</persName> celebrating, the praised apostle
                     <persName type="biblical" key="Paul_Act.7.58">Paul</persName>, who resonates
                  his teaching in the ears of everybody, the hymn of the angels, the never-ending
                  hallelujah, the evangelical voices, the Lord’s commandments, the admonition and
                  counsel of the holy bishops and presbyters, all spirituals, all heavenly things,
                  all relief of salvation and kingdom. Who comes to the church hears that and sees
                  that. What see those who run to the theater? Prostitutes, devilish songs, voices
                  full of filth and anarchy, women dancing, or rather being possessed by a demon.
                  For what does the female dancer? It’s nothing other than that she is voluntarily
                  possessed by a demon. Equally the lyre-player assaults his wooden instrument like
                  a demon. All those spectacles of the theater are demonic, all are causing
                  destruction, all are amusements of demons. <seg type="allusion">That’s why their
                     reward is good-for-nothing. Such was the banquet of <persName type="biblical"
                        key="Herod_Mat.14.1">Herod</persName>. As <persName type="biblical"
                        key="Herodias_Mat.14.3">Herodias</persName> entered, she danced and cut off
                     the head of <persName type="biblical" key="John_Mat.3.1">John the
                        Baptist</persName>,<ref decls="#biblical" cRef="NA:Mt:14:1-10"/></seg> and
                  (then) she inherited the Hades under the earth. Now, those who loved her
                  lascivious dance have their share and their condemnation with her.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
               <p>Now, be content, my beloved, to work on six days for your business and to cease
                  wrongdoings on the day of the Lord. I know many who have troubles with each other
                  and are fighting and say: ‘The day of the Lord comes and we have a trial.’ Oh
                  wretched and miserable man! You are ordered to pray on the day of the Lord, not to
                  organize courts of justice! Now the day of the Lord comes and the one who has a
                  trial premeditates the whole night what he has against his neighbor and when the
                  sunrise comes he arms himself against him. This custom is custom with most people
                  that they sit outside when they leave the church and often the presbyter acts like
                  that in the first place, and then they throw affairs at each other, disputes,
                  insolences, reproaches, and such things and even worse things than that. Then they
                  reenter the church and look angrily on each other like wild animals that creak
                  with their teeth. Woe to the presbyter who sets such things in motion or sits in
                  judgment on the day of the Lord and does not give his prayers to the Lord at the
                  set hour! But if someone tastes from the common things before the release, he is
                  liable to great judgment and punishment. And if he had tasted and has communion in
                  the mysteries, <seg type="allusion">then his part is that of the traitor <persName
                        type="biblical" key="Judas_Mat.10.4">Judas</persName>.<ref decls="#biblical"
                        cRef="NA:Mt:27:5"/><ref decls="#biblical" cRef="NA:Jn:17:12"/><ref
                        decls="#biblical" cRef="NA:Act:1:18-20"/></seg> I know many who tasted and
                  took part on the day of the holy Pascha and woe to their soul, even more, if they
                  are in adult age, that they instead of releasing their sins load even more on
                  themselves. But also who has acknowledged bad deeds to himself and has had
                  communion before he wiped them off through repentance is liable to the same
                  judgment. For the bigger the day the bigger the sin. And those who are not without
                  blame need to be strong until the release and need to have communion in that way.
                  Woe to those who play lyre on the day of the Lord or dance or get judged or sit as
                  judges or work or take an oath or make one swear, that they will be condemned to
                  inextinguishable fire and their part is with the hypocrites. For that day was
                  given to us for prayer and for atonement of evil, for repentance and for
                  salvation, for rest of hired laborers and of servants.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
               <p><quote>For that is the day that the Lord had made. Let us praise and rejoice in
                        it!<ref decls="#biblical" cRef="LXX:Ps:117:24"/></quote> Let us rejoice not
                  befuddled by intoxication and drunkenness, but delighted in the declamation of the
                  divine scriptures! God gave us that day, on which he began to make the world, in
                  which he destroyed the power of death, and he called it the day of the Lord, that
                  beginning with the name of the day itself we respect and keep the commandments of
                  the Lord. A hired laborer goes in his house and dedicates himself to his work and
                  on six days he does not dare to look up and see the sun, where it comes from and
                  where it goes to, but weary in your works the lamentable shatters and weeps, in
                  sweat and in pains, and never is it granted to him to look up or to take a rest,
                  as we said, but he only waits for the day of the Lord, that, if anything, the dirt
                  is shaken off his body, and often you do not even concede him that. And which
                  defense will you have, tell me! Of course, there are some who out of beneficence
                  will say on the day of the Lord: Come here, today let’s help the poor in their
                  work! And who do not know that since they want to do good they sin even more. If
                  you want to help the poor, do not steal the day of God, but give your earnings to
                  the poor, from which you have your revenue. When they are obliged to do your work,
                  then give help to the poor! But when your slaves and your hired laborers and your
                  cattle are obliged to rest, then you take away their rest and give it to the poor.
                  God knows whose work it is! Do not transgress the commandment of the Lord, do not
                  steal his day, do not deprive your slaves and your hired laborers from their rest,
                  do not get separated from the prayer, do not stay away from the church! For
                  nothing is higher than the church, the church is higher than the heaven and
                  brighter than the sun and clearer than the moon and the stars and more valuable
                  than the whole world. I know many who do not enter the church the whole week,
                  often even entirely. And when something bad happens to them because of their
                  ill-doing, they accuse God and not themselves and say: ‘Why has God allowed that
                  to happen?’ And they do not know that as far as they put themselves away from the
                  church as far away is also God from them, as also the prophet says: <quote>Those
                     far away from you perish.<ref decls="#biblical" cRef="LXX:Ps:72:27"
                  /></quote></p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
               <p>That probably will suffice, my brothers, as warning and for the fear of most
                  people. For if that does not suffice and persuade those hearing, then they will
                  also not hear which is greater than that. For it says: ‘For the sensible man one
                  word is sufficient, but even if you explain at length to the foolish, you will not
                  persuade his heart until death.’ You want no evil to come upon you? Do not abuse
                  the day of the Lord, keep away from bad deeds, devote yourself to prayer, stop
                  your mouth to use foul language, get together with pious men, and thank God
                  together with them, and send up praise! For in many ways it is said that that day
                  was given you for prayer and for rest. <quote>This, really, is the day that the
                     Lord had made. Let us praise and rejoice in it!<ref decls="#biblical"
                        cRef="LXX:Ps:117:24"/></quote> And let us send up honor to the one risen on
                  it together with the Father and the Holy Spirit, now, ever and in all eternity!
                  Amen.”</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
