<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema/master/tei-pta.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title xml:lang="la">In paralyticum (Mc 2,1-12)</title>
            <author>
               <persName key="pta0039">(Ps.-?)Johannes Chrysostomus</persName>
            </author>
            <editor>
               <persName xml:id="AvS">Annette von Stockhausen</persName>
               <roleName>Translator</roleName>
               <orgName>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</orgName>
            </editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Berlin-Brandenburgische Akademie der Wissenschaften</authority>
            <distributor>Patristic Text Archive</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available
                        under a Creative Commons Attribution ShareAlike 4.0 International
                        License</licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2019</date>
            <idno type="PTA">pta0039.pta003</idno>
            <idno type="CPG">4857</idno>
            <idno type="BHG"/>
            <idno type="Aldama"/>
            <idno type="Pinakes-Oeuvre">8309</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Deutsche Übersetzung der Edition <ptr target="CPG4857-Edition.xml"/>
            </p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(.+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']/tei:div[@n='$1'])"/>
         </refsDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>
            This file is encoded according to the guidelines of the Patristic Text Archive (PTA). See <ref target="https://pta.bbaw.de/project/encoding-guidelines">https://pta.bbaw.de/project/encoding-guidelines</ref> and <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3737666">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3737666</ref>.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="biblical-quotations"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Biblical quotations are not annotated and not referenced. References follow the scheme declared <ref target="#biblical">above</ref>.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="other-references"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Other references are not annotated and not referenced. References to texts in the PTA follow the scheme declared <ref target="#pta">above (pta)</ref>, references to texts available in the <ref target="https://scaife.perseus.org/">Perseus Digital Library</ref> follow the scheme declared <ref target="#perseus">above (perseus)</ref>. If the referenced text is not available in either repository, the reference for the referenced text is given in the attribute @source in the form “Authorabbrev_Workabbrev_Location”; ancient Greek authors should be referenced according to the lists of H. G. Liddell/R. Scott/H. S. Jones, A Greek - English Lexicon, Oxford 1968 (9th edition) and G. W. H. Lampe, A Patristic Greek Lexicon, Oxford 1987 (3rd edition), for Latin ones the abbreviations of the Thesaurus Linguae Latinae (cf. Index librorum scriptorum inscriptionum ex quibus exempla afferuntur) should be used, with dots in the abbreviations deleted without replacement.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="persons"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Persons are not annotated and not referenced with IDs according to the <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/tipnr_data">TIPNR - Tyndale Individualised Proper Names with all References</ref> list for biblical persons and IDs of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/pta_metadata/blob/main/pta_persons.json">PTA persons index</ref> for all other persons.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="groups"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Groups of persons and organisations are not annotated and not referenced with IDs according to the IDs of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/pta_metadata/blob/main/pta_groups.json">PTA groups index</ref> for all other groups.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="places"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Places are not annotated and not referenced with <ref target="https://pleiades.stoa.org/">Pleiades Gazetteer</ref> IDs.
          </p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p><!--Usage of capitalisation, ν-ephelkystikon, σ: οὕτως, Iota subscriptum/adscriptum, Trema, Enclitics, apostroph/elisions, number signs, splitting of words, nomina sacra, ...--></p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p><!--Usage (and/or normalisation) of full stop, comma, semicolon, question mark, dash and parenthesis--></p>
            </punctuation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="comphistsem">
               <bibl>
          Text Type Classification by <ref target="https://www.comphistsem.org/46.html">"Computational Historical Semantics</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="editionstatus">
               <bibl>
          Patristic Text Archive Status of edition
        </bibl>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition">
                  <catDesc>
            Critical edition in which the text-critical variants have been encoded.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition-no-app">
                  <catDesc>
            Critical edition in which the text-critical variants have not been encoded, e.g. because it is a retro-digitisation of a printed critical edition and for copyright reasons the apparatus cannot be included in the retro-digitisation.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition-outdated">
                  <catDesc>
              Edition which notes text-critical variants, but does not, for example, comprehensively include the manuscripts.
            </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="pre-critical-edition">
                  <catDesc>
              Pre-modern editions (e.g. editions in the Patrologia Graeca or Latina)
            </catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="annotationstatus">
               <bibl>
          Patristic Text Archive Status of annotation
        </bibl>
               <category xml:id="fully-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            All instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="partially-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            Some instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="not-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            No instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="fully-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            All encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="partially-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            Some encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="not-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            No encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <schemaRef key="v3"
                    url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema/master/tei-pta.rng"/>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notBefore="0401" notAfter="0404"/>
            <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/77402394">Constantinopolis</placeName>
         </creation>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#comphistsem">
               <term>Paraenetic</term>
               <term>Sermon</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2023-05-22" who="#AvS">
          Updated file to comply with version 3.0 of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema">TEI-PTA-Schema</ref>
         </change>
         <change who="#AvS" when="2018-05-29">Rohübersetzung</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="de">
      <body>
         <div type="translation"
              xml:lang="deu" corresp="urn:cts:pta:pta0039.pta003.pta-grcBibex"
              n="urn:cts:pta:pta0039.pta003.pta-deuBibex">
            <head>
               <title> Rede unseres unter den Heiligen befindlichen Vaters Chrysostomos, des
                        Erzbischofs von Konstantinopel, über den Gelähmten oder zum zweiten Sonntag
                        der Fastenzeit </title>
            </head>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
               <p>Vorhin hat uns der Prophet die gute Botschaft gebracht und die Geschichte der
                        vorliegenden Wunder niedergeschrieben: <quote>Seid stark,
                            erschlaffte Hände und gelähmte Knie! Ihr Kleinmütigen in eurer Seele,
                            bittet! Seid stark, fürchtet euch nicht! Denn siehe, unser Gott spricht
                            Recht, er wird vergelten und selbst kommen und uns retten. Dann werden
                            die Augen der Blinden geöffnet werden und die Ohren der Tauben hören;
                            dann wird der Lahme wie ein Hirsch umherschweifen und die schwer
                            sprechende Zunge wird klar sein.</quote> Siehst du den Gelähmten wie in
                        einem Bild vorgebildet?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
               <p>Sieh, wie er eben vom Heiland geheilt wird, sieh, wie jetzt das Prophezeite
                        erfüllt wird; <quote>Denn siehe, sagt er, es kommen zu ihm welche, die einen
                            Gelähmten tragen;</quote> und weil sie sich ihm nicht nähern können wegen
                        der Menschenmasse, da graben sie den Ort, an dem er war, auf und lassen den
                        Gelähmten hinunter. Was für ein Glaube derer, die ihn herbeibringen! Die
                        einen haben ihn herbeigebracht und der andere wird gerettet; der Gelähmte
                        war, weil er an Seele und Leib krank war, nicht er selbst; der Heiland
                        bewunderte den Glauben derer, die ihn herbeibrachten, und sagte:
                            <quote>Wegen des Glaubens derer, die dich herbeibrachten, Kind, werden
                            dir deine Sünden genommen.</quote> Was für eine Menschenfreundlichkeit
                        des Arztes! Der Kranke wurde nicht nur geheilt, sondern er nannte ihn auch
                            <quote>Kind</quote> und sagte: <quote>Kind, dir werden deine Sünden
                            genommen.</quote> Denn wie Ärzte zuerst die Ursachen der Krankheiten
                        beseitigen und so die Heilung herbeiführen, so tat das auch der Christus:
                        Denn weil die Ursache der Krankheit die Sünde war, musste er sie zuerst
                        beenden und, nachdem er so das Verborgene vorher gemäßigt hatte, heilte er
                        das Offenbare. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
               <p>Doch wieder murrten die gerne anklagenden Pharisäer und sagten: <quote>Wer
                            ist dieser da, der Blasphemie spricht?</quote> Der Heiland aber machte
                        ihre böse Gesinnung öffentlich und heilte auch das Offenbare, wobei er
                        sagte: <quote>Was ist leichter zu sagen? Dir sind deine Sünden vergeben?
                            Oder zu sagen: Steh auf und gehe umher?</quote> Denn stärker als der
                        Körper ist die Seele. Deswegen hat er zuerst sie und dann den Körper
                        geheilt. Warum werfen ihm also wieder die schamlosen Juden vor, dass er den
                        Gelähmten am Sabbat geheilt hat? Machst du dem Arzt Vorwürfe, der am Sabbat
                        heilt? Mache deiner Frau Vorwürfe, dass sie am Sabbat gebiert! Mache auch
                        der Sonne Vorwürfe, weil sie am Sabbat aufgeht! Mache auch dem Himmel
                        Vorwürfe, weil er am Sabbat den Regen herabschickt! Vielleicht machst du
                        auch der Erde Vorwürfe, weil sie dir am Sabbat Frucht bringt. Wenn du aber
                        den Geschöpfen keine Vorwürfe machst, was rufst du da gegen den Schöpfer,
                        weil er am Sabbat seine Wohltat tut?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
               <p>Doch jene sind undankbar und berauben sich selbst des Königreiches, wir aber
                        erkennen den Wohltäter und bewundern ihn als Heilenden, wir preisen ihn als
                        Wohltäter, denn ihm gebührt die Ehre und die Macht, jetzt und ewig und in
                        alle Ewigkeiten, Amen.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
