<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema/master/tei-pta.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dok. 10: Fragmente eines Briefes des Eusebius von Caesarea an Euphration von Balaneae (Urk. 3)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="AvS">Annette von Stockhausen</persName>
               <resp>Conversion to CTS-compliant PTA TEI.</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Arbeitsstelle Athanasius Werke, FAU Erlangen-Nürnberg</authority>
            <distributor>Patristic Text Archive</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/de/">Available under a Attribution-NonCommercial 3.0 Germany (CC BY-NC 3.0 DE)</licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2018</date>
            <idno type="PTA">pta0100.pta010</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl>
                  <note>Critical edition (without critical apparatus)</note>
                  <title>Athanasius Werke. Band 3 / 1. Teil: Dokumente zur Geschichte des arianischen Streites. Lieferung 3: Bis zur Ekthesis makrostichos</title>
                  <editor>
                     <forename>Hanns Christof</forename>
                     <surname>Brennecke</surname>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <forename>Uta</forename>
                     <surname>Heil</surname>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <forename>Annette</forename>
                     <surname>von Stockhausen</surname>
                  </editor>
                  <editor>
                     <forename>Angelika</forename>
                     <surname>Wintjes</surname>
                  </editor>
                  <pubPlace>Berlin/New York</pubPlace>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="86" to="87">86–87</biblScope>
                  <date when="2007">2007</date>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(.+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']/tei:div[@n='$1'])"/>
         </refsDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>
            This file is encoded according to the guidelines of the Patristic Text Archive (PTA). See <ref target="https://pta.bbaw.de/project/encoding-guidelines">https://pta.bbaw.de/project/encoding-guidelines</ref> and <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3737666">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3737666</ref>.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="biblical-quotations"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Biblical quotations are not annotated and not referenced. References follow the scheme declared <ref target="#biblical">above</ref>.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="other-references"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Other references are not annotated and not referenced. References to texts in the PTA follow the scheme declared <ref target="#pta">above (pta)</ref>, references to texts available in the <ref target="https://scaife.perseus.org/">Perseus Digital Library</ref> follow the scheme declared <ref target="#perseus">above (perseus)</ref>. If the referenced text is not available in either repository, the reference for the referenced text is given in the attribute @source in the form “Authorabbrev_Workabbrev_Location”; ancient Greek authors should be referenced according to the lists of H. G. Liddell/R. Scott/H. S. Jones, A Greek - English Lexicon, Oxford 1968 (9th edition) and G. W. H. Lampe, A Patristic Greek Lexicon, Oxford 1987 (3rd edition), for Latin ones the abbreviations of the Thesaurus Linguae Latinae (cf. Index librorum scriptorum inscriptionum ex quibus exempla afferuntur) should be used, with dots in the abbreviations deleted without replacement.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="persons"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Persons are not annotated and not  referenced with IDs according to the <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/tipnr_data">TIPNR - Tyndale Individualised Proper Names with all References</ref> list for biblical persons and IDs of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/pta_metadata/blob/main/pta_persons.json">PTA persons index</ref> for all other persons.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="groups"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Groups of persons and organisations are not annotated and not referenced with IDs according to the IDs of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/pta_metadata/blob/main/pta_groups.json">PTA groups index</ref> for all other groups.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="places"
                  ana="not-annotated not-identified">
            Places are not annotated and not referenced with <ref target="https://pleiades.stoa.org/">Pleiades Gazetteer</ref> IDs.
          </p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p><!--Usage of capitalisation, ν-ephelkystikon, σ: οὕτως, Iota subscriptum/adscriptum, Trema, Enclitics, apostroph/elisions, number signs, splitting of words, nomina sacra, ...--></p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p><!--Usage (and/or normalisation) of full stop, comma, semicolon, question mark, dash and parenthesis--></p>
            </punctuation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="comphistsem">
               <bibl>
          Text Type Classification by <ref target="https://www.comphistsem.org/46.html">"Computational Historical Semantics</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="editionstatus">
               <bibl>
          Patristic Text Archive Status of edition
        </bibl>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition">
                  <catDesc>
            Critical edition in which the text-critical variants have been encoded.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition-no-app">
                  <catDesc>
            Critical edition in which the text-critical variants have not been encoded, e.g. because it is a retro-digitisation of a printed critical edition and for copyright reasons the apparatus cannot be included in the retro-digitisation.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition-outdated">
                  <catDesc>
              Edition which notes text-critical variants, but does not, for example, comprehensively include the manuscripts.
            </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="pre-critical-edition">
                  <catDesc>
              Pre-modern editions (e.g. editions in the Patrologia Graeca or Latina)
            </catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="annotationstatus">
               <bibl>
          Patristic Text Archive Status of annotation
        </bibl>
               <category xml:id="fully-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            All instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="partially-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            Some instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="not-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            No instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="fully-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            All encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="partially-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            Some encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="not-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            No encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <schemaRef key="v3"
                    url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema/master/tei-pta.rng"/>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notBefore="0030" notAfter="0800"/>
            <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/XXXXX">
                    placeName missing
                </placeName>
         </creation>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#comphistsem">
               <term>
                        Genre missing
                    </term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2023-05-22" who="#AvS">
          Updated file to comply with version 3.0 of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema">TEI-PTA-Schema</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2019-02-10" who="#AvS">Converted to PTA/CapiTainS</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="translation"
              xml:lang="deu"
              n="urn:cts:pta:pta0100.pta010.pta-deu1"
              corresp="urn:cts:pta:pta0100.pta010.pta-grc1">
            <head>
               <title>Dok. 10: Fragmente eines Briefes des Eusebius von Caesarea an Euphration von Balaneae (Urk. 3)</title>
            </head>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
               <p>(Brief) des Eusebius, des Pamphilos' Sohn, an Euphration, dessen Anfang (lautet): Meinem Herrn bekenne ich nach aller Gnade.</p>
               <p>Und nach weiteren Worten:</p>
               <p>Denn wir sagen nicht, daß der Sohn zusammen mit dem Vater existiert, sondern daß der Vater vor dem Sohn existiert. Denn falls sie zusammen existierten, wie kann da der Vater Vater und der Sohn Sohn sein? Oder wie ist der eine Erster, der andere aber Zweiter? Und der eine ungezeugt, der andere aber gezeugt? Denn zwei, die einander genau gleich sind und zusammen existieren, dürften der gleichen Ehre wert gehalten werden und sind entweder beide, wie ich sagte, ungezeugt oder beide gezeugt. Doch keines von beiden ist wahr; denn weder das Ungezeugte noch das Gezeugte dürften beide zugleich existieren, sondern das eine wird für das Erste und für stärker sowohl der Ordnung als auch der Ehre nach als das Zweite gehalten, da es ja für das Zweite auch zur Ursache sowohl für das Sein als auch das So-Sein wurde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
               <p>Abgesehen (davon) hat der Sohn Gottes selbst, der besser als alle genau sich auskennt und weiß, daß er selbst ein anderer als der Vater und geringer und hervorgegangen ist, ganz und gar fromm dies auch uns gelehrt und gesagt: »Der Vater, der mich gesandt hat, ist größer als ich.«</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
               <p>Und es wurde aus demselben Brief vorgelesen:</p>
               <p>Er lehrt, daß derselbe auch der einzig Wahrhaftige ist, indem er sagt: »damit sie dich als den einzig wahrhaftigen Gott erkennen«, nicht so, als ob Gott allein einer wäre, sondern als ob nur ein einzig wahrhaftiger Gott existierte mit der absolut notwendigen Hinzufügung des ›wahrhaftig‹. Denn der Sohn ist auch selbst Gott, aber nicht wahrhaftiger Gott. Denn ein einziger ist auch einzig wahrhaftiger Gott, weil er niemanden vor sich hat. Denn wenn auch der Sohn selbst wahrhaftiger (Gott) ist, dann ist er doch wohl Gott wie ein Abbild des wahrhaftigen Gottes, da »das Wort auch Gott war«, freilich nicht so wie der einzige, wahrhaftige Gott.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
               <p>Er erdreistete sich, das Wort von Gott zu trennen und das Wort einen anderen Gott zu nennen, der im Blick auf sein Wesen und die Macht vom Vater unterschieden ist. Und in welch große Blasphemie er dabei verfiel, kann man klar und leicht an den von ihm geschriebenen Worten lernen. Denn er hat mit eben diesen Worten geschrieben:</p>
               <p>Freilich wird das Bild und das, dessen Abbild es ist, nicht für ein und dasselbe gehalten, sondern (es sind) zwei Wesen, zwei Dinge und zwei Mächte, wie es auch so viele Bezeichnungen gibt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
               <p>Da er den Heiland nur als Menschen erweisen wollte, sagte er folgendes, als ob er uns das größte, unsagbare Geheimnis des Apostels aufdeckte:</p>
               <p>Deswegen hat ganz sicher auch der göttliche Apostel uns die unsagbare und mystische Lehre über Gott gegeben und rief und schrie »Einer ist Gott«, und danach sagt er, nach dem einen Gott ist »ein Mittler Gottes und der Menschen, der Mensch Christus Jesus«.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
