<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema/master/tei-pta.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:lang="en">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Dok. 10: Fragmente eines Briefes des Eusebius von Caesarea an Euphration von Balaneae (Urk. 3)</title>
            <respStmt>
               <persName xml:id="AvS">Annette von Stockhausen</persName>
               <resp>Conversion to CTS-compliant PTA TEI.</resp>
            </respStmt>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>Arbeitsstelle Athanasius Werke, FAU Erlangen-Nürnberg</authority>
            <distributor>Patristic Text Archive</distributor>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License</licence>
            </availability>
            <date>2019</date>
            <idno type="PTA">pta0100.pta010</idno>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl xml:id="Opitz">
                  <note>Critical edition (without critical apparatus)</note>
                  <title>Athanasius Werke. Band 3 / 1. Teil: Urkunden zur Geschichte des arianischen Streites. Lieferung 1-2</title>
                  <editor>
                     <forename>Hans-Georg</forename>
                     <surname>Opitz</surname>
                  </editor>
                  <pubPlace>Berlin/Leipzig</pubPlace>
                  <biblScope unit="page" from="4" to="6">4–6</biblScope>
                  <date from="1934" to="1935">1934-1935</date>
               </bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(.+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='edition']/tei:div[@n='$1'])"/>
         </refsDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <interpretation>
               <p>
            This file is encoded according to the guidelines of the Patristic Text Archive (PTA). See <ref target="https://pta.bbaw.de/project/encoding-guidelines">https://pta.bbaw.de/project/encoding-guidelines</ref> and <ref target="https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3737666">https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.3737666</ref>.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="biblical-quotations"
                  ana="partially-annotated not-identified">
            Biblical quotations are partially annotated and not  referenced. References follow the scheme declared <ref target="#biblical">above</ref>.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="other-references"
                  ana="partially-annotated not-identified">
            Other references are partially annotated and not  referenced. References to texts in the PTA follow the scheme declared <ref target="#pta">above (pta)</ref>, references to texts available in the <ref target="https://scaife.perseus.org/">Perseus Digital Library</ref> follow the scheme declared <ref target="#perseus">above (perseus)</ref>. If the referenced text is not available in either repository, the reference for the referenced text is given in the attribute @source in the form “Authorabbrev_Workabbrev_Location”; ancient Greek authors should be referenced according to the lists of H. G. Liddell/R. Scott/H. S. Jones, A Greek - English Lexicon, Oxford 1968 (9th edition) and G. W. H. Lampe, A Patristic Greek Lexicon, Oxford 1987 (3rd edition), for Latin ones the abbreviations of the Thesaurus Linguae Latinae (cf. Index librorum scriptorum inscriptionum ex quibus exempla afferuntur) should be used, with dots in the abbreviations deleted without replacement.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="persons"
                  ana="partially-annotated not-identified">
            Persons are partially annotated and not  referenced with IDs according to the <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/tipnr_data">TIPNR - Tyndale Individualised Proper Names with all References</ref> list for biblical persons and IDs of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/pta_metadata/blob/main/pta_persons.json">PTA persons index</ref> for all other persons.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="groups"
                  ana="partially-annotated not-identified">
            Groups of persons and organisations are partially annotated and not  referenced with IDs according to the IDs of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/pta_metadata/blob/main/pta_groups.json">PTA groups index</ref> for all other groups.
          </p>
               <p xml:id="places"
                  ana="partially-annotated not-identified">
            Places are partially annotated and not  referenced with <ref target="https://pleiades.stoa.org/">Pleiades Gazetteer</ref> IDs.
          </p>
            </interpretation>
            <normalization>
               <p><!--Usage of capitalisation, ν-ephelkystikon, σ: οὕτως, Iota subscriptum/adscriptum, Trema, Enclitics, apostroph/elisions, number signs, splitting of words, nomina sacra, ...--></p>
            </normalization>
            <punctuation>
               <p><!--Usage (and/or normalisation) of full stop, comma, semicolon, question mark, dash and parenthesis--></p>
            </punctuation>
         </editorialDecl>
         <classDecl>
            <taxonomy xml:id="comphistsem">
               <bibl>
          Text Type Classification by <ref target="https://www.comphistsem.org/46.html">"Computational Historical Semantics</ref>
               </bibl>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="editionstatus">
               <bibl>
          Patristic Text Archive Status of edition
        </bibl>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition">
                  <catDesc>
            Critical edition in which the text-critical variants have been encoded.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition-no-app">
                  <catDesc>
            Critical edition in which the text-critical variants have not been encoded, e.g. because it is a retro-digitisation of a printed critical edition and for copyright reasons the apparatus cannot be included in the retro-digitisation.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="critical-edition-outdated">
                  <catDesc>
              Edition which notes text-critical variants, but does not, for example, comprehensively include the manuscripts.
            </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="pre-critical-edition">
                  <catDesc>
              Pre-modern editions (e.g. editions in the Patrologia Graeca or Latina)
            </catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
            <taxonomy xml:id="annotationstatus">
               <bibl>
          Patristic Text Archive Status of annotation
        </bibl>
               <category xml:id="fully-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            All instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="partially-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            Some instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="not-annotated">
                  <catDesc>
            No instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are encoded with the respective element.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="fully-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            All encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="partially-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            Some encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data
          </catDesc>
               </category>
               <category xml:id="not-identified">
                  <catDesc>
            No encoded instances of a phenomenon (e.g. biblical quotations, persons, places) are identified with the respective norm data.
          </catDesc>
               </category>
            </taxonomy>
         </classDecl>
         <schemaRef key="v3"
                    url="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema/master/tei-pta.rng"/>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <creation>
            <date notBefore="0030" notAfter="0800"/>
            <placeName ref="https://pleiades.stoa.org/places/XXXXX">
                    placeName missing
                </placeName>
         </creation>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="#comphistsem">
               <term>
                        Genre missing
                    </term>
            </keywords>
            <keywords scheme="#editionstatus">
               <term>critical-edition-no-app</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc status="draft">
         <change when="2023-05-22" who="#AvS">
          Updated file to comply with version 3.0 of <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema">TEI-PTA-Schema</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2021-02-04" who="#AvS">Tagged places and persons</change>
         <change when="2019-12-17" who="#AvS">
                Updated file to comply with version 1.2 of
                <ref target="https://github.com/PatristicTextArchive/Schema">TEI-PTA-Schema</ref>
         </change>
         <change when="2019-02-10" who="#AvS">Converted to PTA/CapiTainS</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="edition"
              xml:lang="grc"
              n="urn:cts:pta:pta0100.pta010.pta-grc1">
            <head>
               <title>Urkunde 3. Brief des Euseb von Cäsarea an Euphration von Balaneä.</title>
            </head>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
               <p>
                  <persName>Εὐσεβίου</persName> τοῦ <persName>Παμφίλου</persName> πρὸς <persName>Εὐφρατίωνα</persName>. οὗ ἡ ἀρχή: Τῷ δεσπότῃ μου κατὰ πάντα χάριν ὁμολογῶ.</p>
               <p>Καὶ μεθ’ ἕτερα·</p>
               <p>Οὐ γὰρ συνυπάρχειν φαμὲν τὸν υἱὸν τῷ πατρί, προυπάρχειν δὲ τὸν πατέρα τοῦ υἱοῦ. ἐὰν γὰρ συνυπάρχωσι, πῶς ἔσται ὁ πατὴρ πατὴρ καὶ ὁ υἱὸς υἱός; ἢ πῶς ὁ μὲν πρῶτος, ὁ δὲ δεύτερος; καὶ ὁ μὲν ἀγέννητος, ὁ δὲ γεννητός; δύο γὰρ ἐξ ἴσου ὁμοίως ἀλλήλοις συνυπάρχοντα ἰσότιμα ἂν νοοῖντο καὶ ἤτοι ἄμφω, ὡς ἔφην, ἀγέννητα ἢ ἑκάτερα γεννητά. ἀλλ’ οὐδέτερον τούτων ἀληθές· οὔτε γὰρ τὸ ἀγέννητον οὔτε τὸ γεννητὸν ἂν εἴη. ἀλλὰ τὸ μὲν καὶ πρῶτον καὶ κρεῖττον καὶ τάξει καὶ τιμῇ τοῦ δευτέρου ἡγεῖται, ὡς ἂν καὶ τοῦ εἶναι καὶ τοῦ τοιῶσδε εἶναι τῷ δευτέρῳ αἴτιον γεγενημένον.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
               <p>Πλὴν αὐτὸς ὁ πάντων μᾶλλον ἀκριβῶς ἐπιστάμενος υἱὸς τοῦ θεοῦ ἕτερον ἑαυτὸν εἰδὼς τοῦ πατρὸς καὶ μείω καὶ ὑποβεβηκότα, εὖ μάλα εὐσεβῶς τοῦτο καὶ ἡμᾶς διδάσκει λέγων· »ὁ πατὴρ ὁ πέμψας με μείζων μού ἐστι«.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
               <p>Καὶ ἀνεγνώσθη ἐκ τῆς αὐτῆς ἐπιστολῆς·</p>
               <p>Τὸν αὐτὸν δὲ καὶ μόνον ἀληθινὸν εἶναι διδάσκει δι ̓ ὧν φησιν· »ἶνα γινώσκωσί σε τὸν μόνον ἀληθινὸν θεόν«, οὐχὶ ὡς ἑνὸς ὄντος μόνου τοῦ θεοῦ, ἀλλ’ ̓ ὡς ἑνὸς ὄντος μόνου ἀληθινοῦ θεοῦ μετὰ προσθήκης ἀναγκαιοτάτης τοῦ ἀληθινοῦ. ἐπεὶ καὶ αὐτὸς θεὸς μὲν ὁ υἱός, ἀλλ ̓ οὐκ ἀληθινὸς θεός. εἷς γάρ ἐστι καὶ μόνος ἀληθινὸς θεὸς διὰ τὸ μὴ ἔχειν πρὸ αὐτοῦ τινα. εἰ δὲ καὶ αὐτὸς ὁ υἱὸς ἀληθινός, ἀλλ’ ὡς εἰκὼν τοῦ ἀληθινοῦ θεοῦ εἴη ἂν καὶ θεός, ἐπεὶ »καὶ θεὸς ἧν ὁ λόγος«, οὐ μὴν ὡς ὁ μόνος ἀληθινὸς θεός.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
               <p>Διελεῖν γὰρ τὸν λόγον τοῦ θεοῦ τολμήσας καὶ ἕτερον θεὸν τὸν λόγον ὀνομάσαι, οὐσίᾳ τε καὶ δυνάμει διεστῶτα τοῦ πατρός, εἰς ὅσην βλασφημίαν ἐκπέπτωκεν ἔνεστιν σαφῶς ἀπ’ αὐτῶν τῶν ὑπ’ αὐτοῦ γραφέντων ῥητῶν ῥᾳδίως μανθάνειν. γέγραφεν δ’ αὐταῖς λέξεσιν οὕτως·</p>
               <p>Οὐ δήπου δὲ ἡ εἰκὼν καὶ τὸ οὗ ἐστιν ἡ εἰκὼν ἓν καὶ ταὐτὸν ἐπινοεῖται, ἀλλὰ δύο μὲν οὐσίαι καὶ δύο πράγματα καὶ δύο δυνάμεις, ὡς καὶ τοσαῦται προσηγορίαι.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
               <p>Ἄνθρωπον γὰρ μόνον τὸν σωτῆρα δεῖξαι βουλόμενος, ὡς μέγιστον ἡμῖν ἀπόρρητον τοῦ ἀποστόλου ἀνακαλύπτων μυστήριον, οὕτως ἔφη·</p>
               <p>Διὸ σαφέστατα καὶ ὁ θεῖος ἀπόστολος τὴν ἀπόρρητον ἡμῖν καὶ μυστικὴν παραδιδοὺς θεολογίαν βοᾷ καὶ κέκραγεν »εἷς ὁ θεός«, εἶτα μετὰ τὸν ἕνα θεόν φησιν »εἷς μεσίτης θεοῦ καὶ ἀνθρώπων, ἄνθρωπος <persName>Χριστός Ἰησοῦς</persName>«.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
